this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
so welcome listeners to a new episode of
software engineering radio this episode
is once again programming language
episode it's one of my favorite kind of
episodes because you know learning
programming language concepts at least
the concept if you don't learn the
language is very useful and this time
and this time we are covering a very new
language called yoke and at the other
end of the Skype connection is hola
beanie I Lauder and he's obviously the
guy who created yoke so he should be
able to talk about it so hola why don't
you introduce yourself to our listeners
before we start hope talking about yoke
ok so very quickly my name is Ola beanie
I live in Sweden I'm a Swede I work with
taught works globally and I've done that
for tuna of years doing all kinds of
different things including consulting I
my mines main time is actually spent
doing JRuby core development that's
basically my my background yeah
I knew that you had this background but
I wasn't aware that you're still doing
it oh yes I am okay you don't talk much
about that publicly you basically talk
about yolk yeah I know I know but I'm
slugging away doing stuff this summer I
wrote a new yam land you know a few
things like that so it happens and I
also do it for as consulting part for
for thought works okay so um okay so
then then I would assume that yolk is
somehow inspired by Ruby or but we'll
talk about that later so so what is yolk
can you give a brief overview in like
five sentences or something so first
it's actually I okey okay
no worries so I okey it's an experiment
that's that's really the first point
it's an experiment in expressiveness its
secondly a dynamic strongly typed
prototype based object-oriented language
that's basically the core of it and it's
got the same kind of macro facilities as
as Lisp for example while still having
enough syntax to feel like Ruby circa of
the main points of language
okay and we'll talk about many of these
things in detail of course but so you
already said it's an experiment so my
next question would be why yet another
language and I guess you kind of
answered it already you wanted to show
something with that language as opposed
to necessarily you know having another
it's a production language out there so
what's the goal of the experiment yes so
as I mentioned expressiveness the whole
it's kind of interesting I'm I'm a
language geek so I know a lot of
languages I think it's really really
funny and relaxing to different to read
language specs and so on and one of my
absolute favorite languages when it
comes to expressiveness is Common Lisp
MLS pad in general but let's be common
lisp is definitely the pinnacle for me
of both being a production language and
and being something that is extremely
expressive and allow you to basically
just form the language that you want to
use to solve the problem and then solve
the problem in it but when you start
looking at the spec you you'll start
reading a few magic sentences that crop
up on almost every page in the in the
common land become wisp spec and that's
basically that the committee that design
Common Lisp made this in this decision
to make it easy for implementers to
implement it efficiently so what I
started thinking about is well okay
so if the most expressive language I
know was compromised to make it
performant what does that mean does it
mean that if I don't care about
performance maybe I'll get a language
that is even more expressive so that's
kind of the goal I want to see if if
Lisp really is the most expressive you
can get or if you can get any higher on
the scale of expressiveness how would
you define or illustrate expressiveness
yeah and that's a very good point
because that turns out to be the problem
I do have a paper of my own my desktop
if I haven't read it read yet about an
objective measure of expressiveness but
I haven't really found anyone that can
actually define expressiveness I've
tried several different things sometimes
people say try try to use power as a
synonym or they use abstraction
capability stuff like that but it
they have the same problem when it comes
to defining them so at the end of the
day for me expressiveness is a very
subjective thing
it basically means how large is that or
how small is the difference sorry the
distance from how I think about a
problem to how I express it in code if I
can think about a problem and and just
take that thinking and put that into
code directly without any translation
then that means that language is very
expressive and the other way around if I
have to muck around trying to figure out
how to organize it into a Java class
hierarchy and that in all this staticky
wash or whatever I need to do then
that's probably not as expressive right
okay and we'll probably see through the
episode how you approach the problem or
the challenge of making things more
expressive and then the listeners can
judge for themselves whether they think
that's more expressive than say Java so
I mean the next thing I've written down
here was the set of languages that it
inspired ioki and obviously I guess it's
probably Lisp since you've already
mentioned that so any any other
influences well io is actually a
language that is the closest kin
apparent that's where some of the
semantics and some of the syntax came
from IO is a very small language - it's
a it's actually a very nice language but
they didn't go far enough when it came
to expressiveness so I wanted to to get
further than that obviously Common Lisp
is definitely a more from a philosophy
standpoint but also when it comes to
macros and stuff like that it's more
like Common Lisp rupee has influenced a
little bit when it comes to the syntax
not how eccentric works but what what
what the syntax actually looks like but
the most that Ruby inspired is to
standard library with the core library
so the core library you will recognize
yourself if you come from a ruby
background and self is actually also a
quite common parent see prototype stuff
exactly something that I was reminded
although right now I can't remember
where and when this thing popped to my
mind was a small talk I mean obviously
everything is objects and messages yeah
well smell itself is a small talk well
it's not necessarily well okay yeah
dialect kind of yeah
yeah it's itself is definitely
considered part of the small talk family
okay yeah well okay yeah then then I
guess we were on the same same page yeah
okay so I guess you already talked about
the syntax being a bit different than
Lisp I mean I always joked that Lisp has
no syntax and of course if you if you
can make your users write down abstract
syntax trees that's very convenient yeah
so how does yoki I probably pronounce it
wrong again as a different-- and you
know what what what role do messages
play and then and that's that yes it's
interesting that you bring up the whole
Lisp and syntax thing because one of the
things that I think the list community
got wrong is that syntax actually just
matter and I'm saying that it doesn't
matter it doesn't really help to help
most of the programs I think that you
can make code that is more readable and
and easier to read and easier to
maintain if you have a small amount of
syntax for LC I agree but obviously the
the main advantage of being in Lisp is
the fact that this if you don't have any
syntax it makes it very very easy to to
do macros you have you get the Home icon
Institute for free so I didn't really
want to get rid of that I thought it was
really really powerful and I thought it
was really necessary for ioki to have
the kind of macro facilities so what I
ended up doing is that I'd so i okay
basically has two different layers of
syntax the first one that is actually
the one that is parsed is another truck
passes by outside here they do some
construction work in my part actually I
didn't hear it so no problem okay good
now so the first stage is this is the
parser that parser is extremely simple
it really only does whatever is
necessary and it doesn't really
distinguish between it doesn't look it
doesn't look at things like
operator precedence it doesn't really do
anything of those fancy things the only
thing it does is to parse messages and
arguments to to messages and the second
stage is called operator shuffling and
the operator shuffling steps that is
really where you have precedence between
things where things like assignment is
actually rearranged into an assignment
message and a few things like that so
can you can you give an example of for
example how the assignment looks in in
in the parsed syntax and what it's
shuffled to well I mean the first step
so yeah the first thing you have to
realize if you come if you come from if
you familiar itself for i/o for example
is that I don't use dots for I don't use
dots for method calls
it's very spaces okay so say for example
I have an object called foo and I want
to set the X property or or I want to
set X on through to the value 42 so in
ioki I write foo space x space equals
space 42 and that's how that's exactly
how the parser will parse that it will
parse that into four four messages
basically the foo message and then the
bar message and then an equals message
and then the 42 message that's that's a
different thing there the 42 thing we're
gonna get back to literals later I think
because they are kind of interesting to
you but so that's that's what the ast
will look like before operator shuffling
so you can also say that the operator
chef or the Parsee step the first
parsing step is or singing a canonical
syntax and then the operators shuffling
rearranges or actually you could say the
parser step parses to a row Sinta to a
raw AST thing rearrange it to the
canonical 3 so after the after the
operator shuffling step the the actual
new ast will say foo equal sign and then
the equal sign will have two arguments
where the first argument is X and the
second argument is
- so assignment is just a message and
where you send in the name of the
variable to set and the values to set it
to okay and the same kind of thing hat
+ and a surplus and multiplication for
example operator shuffling will make
sure that you get the right Kenneth as
in yeah so so in some sense operators
aren't anything special once you've done
the operator shuffling they are just
messages it's so they're not they're not
special before either actually the only
thing that is that makes something an
operator is if they are in the operator
shuffling tables and that's something
that you can change at runtime if you
want you okay because I mean what I was
what I meant by special was that they
can be used in different places and in
different ways which is then resolved by
operator shuffling yeah
exactly it's a everything you can use
this as an operator it's just a message
and you can write the canonical syntax
yourself if you want to so if you really
want to send should equal sign or
something like that directly you can
write it that way instead and it works
out correctly to that syntax it's
obviously more like this yeah even
though it's it's outside in so the the
name is coming outside parentheses okay
so in your example with foo x equals 42
you said that you have four messages the
foo also being a message now the
question is I mean I can imagine that
you sent the X message to the food
thingy but the food is the first message
who do you send it to oh that's so
everything everything you know yogi
execute against the receiver this is
this is kind of the basic small talk
yeah idea everything needs to have a
receiver and the implicit receiver in a
specific context like I call it ground
with lower G so that's kind of the the
receiver when you don't have an explicit
receiver it's going to be the ground I
didn't want to use context because
context is one of those words in CES
that is really really overloaded yeah so
I use ground instead and if you do this
at the top level you the the default
ground
there's gonna be ground with capital G I
know that's confusing but it does make
sense the interesting thing about ground
and we haven't really talked about this
yet but as it turns out ground is
actually in the inheritance chain which
we which means that every object you
create will have ground as one of the
parents so if you define something at
the top level that will actually be
defined in the ground object which means
that it will will be available to all
objects that are part of the regular
hierarchies okay so in some sense that's
a fancy way of doing global global yes
except that it is in global because you
can actually do things that don't have
access everything in IO key is actually
a namespace so nil and true and false
are also messages and they are also
living on one of the ground of the
extent and you can create new objects
that don't really take part of this
inheritance chain so everything just
looked up through the inheritance and
you can you can tune that if you want to
I understand why this is nice from a
let's say you know making everything
built from the same building blocks kind
of thing but but what's the benefit in
practice I mean the problem with global
variables is that you can have side
effects you know you you you have
effects on global state that is not
explicitly you know available through
some kind of dependency analysis and
whatever what's the what's the advantage
of doing it through ground actually I
mean that future of the whole thing not
having Global's wasn't something I
designed in okay just turned out that
way from from some of the other design
goals after language where simplicity of
the simplicity of the model was really
the main design goal that made it happen
so why do I need to have two different
naming scopes if I can get away with
just having one for example okay so so
not having Global's was actually just a
side effect of that okay good
so let's you already talked about
inheritance and stuff so I guess objects
are an important building block of ioki
you already said that this is a pro
based language so you don't have classes
so I guess most of our listeners since
we didn't have an episode on self yet
you might have to explain what what it
means to be a protein-based language
okay so the basic idea here is that you
don't have most object-oriented
languages sir
except for common lisp which are
actually welcome Lisp has three
different kinds of objects but but most
object-oriented languages are falling
into the whole class-based
object-oriented paradigm where you have
classes that contains methods and then
the you have the objects that are off
the classes in some way now in some
languages small talk is a typical
example the classes in themself are also
objects but there are still special
orbit since they can contain methods yes
a prototype based language just removes
the whole idea of classes and makes s
that everything can have objects there
is no distinction there are no there is
only one kind of object and that object
can have slots or or methods or whatever
you want to call them now there are a
few different ways of doing that there
are two main paradigms of doing the
first one is where you just every time
you create a new object you take it from
an existing object so now you copy
everything inside of that object this is
the method that self uses that's not the
way ioki works and for example
javascript is another duck song yeah the
language that doesn't do that instead
these languages keep a pointer to the
object they was they were created from
and when you look up something you start
looking up in the object itself and then
you if you can't find it you look up in
all the parents right right so in a yogi
an object is actually very very simple
an object really has two things in it
it's got a set of cells and those cells
those cells are more or less like slots
or or a property soon at languages
they're binding between a name and a
value and they have a set of mimics and
the mimics are kind of the parents I
used the word mimics in in because I one
of the things that I've tried to do
since is an experiment I try to see what
happens if I change the names of the
core concept
I don't want people have preconceived
notions about what things mean just
because they used the same name yeah so
the cells and mixes that or mimics a
typical example of this now if you want
to understand what why I choose to would
mimic it's actually quite easy to
understand say you have this object that
we already have and you want to create a
new object based on that what we really
want is a new object that mimics the
original object that behaves just like
it except a few cases where it doesn't
so mimic actually makes sense from that
perspective mm-hm so two things that I
just noticed or think I noticed one is
that in that model delegation and
inheritance are somehow kind of the same
thing right
because you know not exactly you can
still do delegation by having cells
inside of the inside of the object that
you delegate stuff to yeah but I mean
looking something up in the parent is
also a delegation to an object that has
you know that one of your mimic pointers
point to yeah true absolutely so it's a
much more homogeneous approach to things
interestingly enough I haven't thought
about it that way but actually actually
makes sense and it turns out that the
ioki inheritance chains have a tendency
to be a little bit larger than the the
most class-based object-oriented
languages inheritance trees what do you
do in case of quote multiple inheritance
if you have several mimics that happen
to provide
contents for the same cells so in other
words you could if object if an object
doesn't have something in the cell you
delegate the look up to the mimics and
you find something in more than one
mimic what do you do it's just basically
the first one wins
so I okay look at procedure is actually
quite flexible it's also deterministic
it's basically it's basically
depth-first no actually yeah its
depth-first left-to-right and since you
can change the mimics at runtime you can
have zero or more mimics that means that
you can do some pretty strange stuff you
can have recursive mimic chains for
example okay I have a beak that mimics
itself if you really want to and why is
that well it's more like
park right I mean that's a well I mean
it's probably a bug in almost all cases
but in some case it's kind of useful to
have objects that depend on each other
right I haven't seen the use case
without a reality but I didn't really
want to disallow it so it's handled
correctly
basically ioki just uses the first one
that can find right okay and then there
is another thing which is that you can
easily add behavior since behaviors just
slotko as cell contents you can easily
add behavior to only one object and not
two classes I know that the term class
doesn't make sense but in the old world
or in the class based languages world
you would be able to add stuff to only
one object as opposed to the class yes
true I mean that that's one of the
things in Ruby you can do yeah it Ruby
it's actually I mean it's actually faked
because when you add a new method to to
a specific object there's actually a new
in a new class springs into existence
that you can't see that that's cysts
between the real class and the object
you know yoki the so I want to take a
step back and just say quickly why I
choose the whole prototype based model
because it's it's also based on the core
core principles behind the language
except for expressiveness I tend to
believe that simplicity is really really
important and one of those things is
basically if you have two kinds of
objects you need to handle them in the
runtime but if you so it makes sense to
just have one kind of object because
that makes the whole runtime model
simpler simpler to understand so that
was kind of the main reason it's just
because of simplicity I mean this this
whole discussion about simplicity I
think is extremely interesting because I
mean if you look at Lisp right it's a
very simple language it only has
basically one concept which is lists
okay and then there are macros and
special forms but I would argue that
Common Lisp is pretty complex I mean
that not the Common Lisp standard at the
original scheme like lisps the thing is
you know pure Lisp
merciless was actually dynamically
scoped okay like at all my point is
trying to get to something else which is
on the other hand other people say Java
is very simple
only has three concepts like classes
methods and and you know properties and
then a bunch of statements and
expressions so I think the question of
what constitutes of what constitutes a
simple language is not quite obvious
because if you say it has fewer concepts
so it's simple so it's very powerful
doesn't mean that it's easy to use
because you have to now kind of assemble
more higher level abstractions from
those simple concepts see what I'm
getting at I I do understand even though
I would never argue that Java is a
simple language the the reason I've say
for example that ioki is very simple is
because I can I've just described all
big model they'll be mobile as
everything in language uses is the whole
idea of cells and mimics that's that's
the only thing that exists see if I if I
take it to an extreme I can give you a
much more simple language yeah which is
basically it's right you have only zero
and once you can expect everything in
terms of zeros and ones but yeah sure
but you have no semantics on the bits if
you actually want to semantics on them
you'll have to assign you'll have to say
this bit pattern does this okay so I
would say the the absolutely simplest
model that you can that you can say that
is the simplest one that can describe
everything is actually lambda calculus
is basically the simplicity as is core
because you can represent all the other
things
ioki is not really exactly that simple
it's slightly more complex than the list
model but it's not much more complex of
mostly start defined in terms of special
forms I think that the standard list one
five forms they need about seven special
forms to describe it and an IO key is
slightly more complicated
the recent io key is a little bit more
complex is because because of they'll be
to orientation because you have trial
receiver for everything which makes the
which makes it's definitely an integral
part of the language and and it's
definitely part of it what makes it
powerful yeah so you don't need an
explicit module system or package system
because you already have everything
names based mm-hm
so I guess one one outcome of the
experiment will be whether Lisp didn't
catch on in mainstream because it's so
simple
the terms you've just defined it or
because of the you know lots of
irritating silly parentheses so so you
see I mean maybe maybe yoke is sorry I
okay it's as simple but but it removes
some of the awkwardness of how Lisp
looks and and the experiment will be
maybe whether then it can catch on and
people consider this kind of simplicity
as as really simple yeah it's gonna be
interesting to see what happens with
that one I mean I'm gonna be happy if if
in five years any other language have
adopted some of the ideas in from my
okay that's definitely gonna be
successful my prestigious okay um that
was kind of a divergent let's go back to
the to the object thing so what do you
do if you want to define something that
plays the role of what classes play in
class-based languages so how do you
define something of which you can define
instances or mimics how do you go about
that well I mean there is no real
class-based thing obviously but I do
have a convention that if you name
something that starts with a capital
letter okay that will be considered as
the kind where a kind is kind of a way
of talking about classes so for example
list with a capital L is actually the
kind that all the other with all the
other lists in the system are based on
but but that's I mean that's just
convention it's something that the
runtime system knows a little bit about
so if you if you print one of those outs
with the standard default print print
statements you you will get something
that says that this is a list instead of
saying it's a it's an origin yeah
whatever okay and and I guess that the
act of defining a kind right of an
object with a capital first letter is
itself a a program in the sense that it
happens dynamically by executing that
program just like in Ruby right yes
absolutely there is no defining there
are no keywords in ioki at all so there
is no definition happening in fact the
only thing you do you create a new
object you sign that your name and as we
talked about earlier as
is just a message sent to so all those
things there is nothing there is nothing
really that you could say is defining
yeah okay and and the last question is
in this space I guess the fact that it's
dynamically typed is mandatory right I
mean if you don't have classes what
would a compile type compile time type
checker do right that's interesting yeah
and it's something that I'm actually
been thinking about that's that's
definitely the future but I do have some
ideas about how to make a statically
typed version of ioki not exactly like
Aoki but I have some ideas about how you
can combine first of all obviously as
you say if you if you can't have any
static classes you need to figure out
another way so what you need is to do a
type inferred fully typing for an engine
for prototype bastes object-oriented
language yes once you have that you can
also start applying things I'm not sure
if your if you're familiar with
structural typing I am yes I think that
you can use the same kind of approach
and you can talk about structural values
I'm this is if I ever have five years
I'm gonna take those five years off and
do a PhD based on those things yeah I'm
not sure if it's ever gonna happen but I
do think it's possible I mean the idea
of being able to add things at runtime
to objects kind of flies in the face
directly to static typing because you
would never be able to use it from
statically typed code because it
obviously doesn't know about it sure and
obviously the language that I would be
doing would not be exactly like a yeah
it would be a kind of a dialect of it
but I I haven't really gotten that
foreign thinking because I'm and I okay
is still is still not a year old from
the first really it's a very young
language and we'll talk about the status
off of ioki and who uses in stuff later
so the the other thing if we have
objects and we can send messages to
these objects then we probably need to
have something like message sorry
methods that kind of are invoked if the
message with a corresponding name is
sent to the object blah blah blah so can
you talk a little about methods yeah
so a basically you create a method by
sending the message method with some
code to it and you get back something
that is a default method now these are
obvious too and you can create them at
runtime because everything is runtime
and IO key you can create your them the
macro facilities actually allow you to
manipulate code in such a way that you
can create your own implementation of
methods that work differently if you
want to and so on mmm there it's yeah I
mean methods are basically things that
can be activated which means that they
have a protocol for how they handled a
being sent a message okay and they
probably also define some kind of local
scope yes they do have a local scope
that local scope actually happens to
just be another ioki object okay so a
local scope is actually an IO key or
because so you don't have really local
variables you just have a local scope an
IO key object that you have those
variables on so it means there is
another ground yeah well so when you
call a method or when a method gets
activated the current lower case ground
is gonna be the current context which is
gonna be an array ochio be a chest okay
and that I and that albeit obviously
have also some some some neat stuff that
makes possible to call methods on the
enclosing object and and so on or the
actual receiver of the message okay
there are also macros which people might
know from Lisp which is in Lisp is
basically a way of you know defining
syntactic forms that are then translated
down to the usual you know list thing so
order macros in in IO key yeah they're
pretty different actually I sometimes I
think it was a mistake to call the
macros but but that's I mean they used
for things that macro see and really use
for that last step they're just a very
quick step back there are actually more
kinds of code in IO key so the first
kind of code that you can work with is
actually messages you can work with roll
mess
and messages is how you it the message
object is kind of the basis of the ast
that's the only node of the ast so you
can work with these at runtime create
new ones and modified at Metron time you
have methods there are default mattes
you have also lexical blocks one second
you said methods are you mentioned
default methods several times I don't
know what this means
sorry so if you call them the method
method you will give back something that
mimics default method okay I see it's
just a kind of all the older methods in
ioki because but so that means you could
write another method which has a
different name let's say blah method
which creates something that mimics
another method object and therefore
behaves somewhat differently yes
absolutely that's a typical example the
way I do interaction with with Java for
example it doesn't actually use default
method it instead it uses something
called native method yeah Tuvok Java
methods okay it reminds me a little bit
of the meta object protocol stuff where
you can change the nature of the things
from which your program is built yes yes
definitely I definitely hit I've got
lots of ideas from that point you okay
I okay so it's a large mix of everything
I've ever read anyway there are two
kinds of macros actually so the first
kind the first one is what you get if
you called macro the second one I call
syntactic macros the difference is that
macros are actually executed at runtime
there will always be executed the
difference is that they do they take
their arguments as code and they can
change them and do stuff with them so it
also means that the arguments are not
evaluated upon exactly they can be
evaluated when the macro feels like
doing it or however the macro feels like
doing it after doing some stuff with
them but they don't have to be evaluated
at all which means that you can in most
cases in case it's like we're in Ruby
you would probably use a block
ioki actually uses macro so for example
most of the innumerable methods are
implemented using
Makris instead of using something else I
don't use lexical blocks specifically at
those points because it turns out to
become necessary to have to create
lexical blocks all over the place
okay so can you give an example of where
a macro can afford of what you would use
a macro for like you said the
innumerable already but maybe a simple
hello world kind of macro where it's
important to understand that the
arguments are not immediately evaluated
yeah that's slightly trickier because
the whole point about macros is that
they allow you to do abstraction on code
right an abstraction on code is tricky
to explain and a hello or a logic on say
well I mean obviously yes actually yeah
there is there is a fairly simple one
you could actually do take if yes
actually had that in mind yeah
if is a typical example because you
really don't want to evaluate both the
then or the else branches until you know
what the result of the first arguments
gonna be so first of all you'll have to
evaluate the first argument if and then
based on what value that is you evaluate
either the second one or the third one
of the arguments but not both of them
right so that's also I think they're the
canonical canonical example for macros
exactly yeah
yeah I should have come up with that
earlier you said that there are also
that so I'm not sure if you meant that
when you said syntactic macros there is
the kind of a way of defining syntax in
yeah okay yeah that's that's also an
unfortunate naming that I probably
should have got away from that the
difference between a syntax macro and a
regular macro in ioki is actually that
theme and this is yeah it's I should
probably have called him semantics
macros but I'm not sure if that would
have made sense the syntactic macros
work the first time they're called at a
specific place the first time I message
is sent to a syntax macro they are
expected to return new code and that
code will be ripped
placing the the message sent to the
syntax macro at that place in the ast
right that's more like the common lisp
version of expanding a macro and
inserting that at place so but it means
that so okay so
ioki doesn't have keywords obviously now
if I wanted to introduce keywords or
something that acts as keywords in let's
say an internal DSL yet
I mean keywords and debts and such as
constants or something or symbols or
whatever how would I go about that using
the macro facility well I would probably
one of those things with the ast that
comes as a surprise to some people is
that you actually can say say that I
call a macro if I call the macro the
first thing I do in a file if I say foo
yeah that thing is a macro that macro
can actually walk the whole the whole
ast for that file if it wants to and it
can find all those key words shouldn't
do something with them that's one way of
doing it another way of doing it but the
important thing to remember about these
macros is that they're still scoped the
same way as everything else okay so
they're looked up their objects in
themselves these macros and they are
looked up the same way and if it's so
you still I mean if you want to have
something that works the same no matter
what you'll have to find a way of you'll
have to find a way of not having it
evaluated in the same namespace
requirements that's the rest of ioki and
the best and the easiest way of doing
that is to have a top-level macro
invocation that actually changes the AC
for everything beneath it but that's
kind of tricky the other thing that I've
been thinking about doing because I
actually quite recently rewrote my
parson from scratch I actually went away
from antler I get some really good
benefits from from doing that antler was
not really look really rightful for the
kind of requirements that I had for ioki
but it turns out the the require it's
now gonna be pretty simple for me if I
want you to add an extensible parser yes
you know I'd kind of
- Slava festive about this for example
adding kind of parsing words or reading
my cruciferous background yeah I mean
that that's I think you've might have
heard about convert where you can define
grammars inside of the of the language
and then parse the grammar and
automatically well not automatically but
as part of the compilation process
translate them to to an AST of the of
the base language of converge and reno
macros are something along those ways
you can just you know feed in any kind
of text and the responsibility of the
reader macro would be to create an AST
from it
yeah yeah the difference is I'm not sure
if the it's possible that's how I'm
gonna do read a macros but I also might
make read a macro something run time
okay I'm not sure I haven't decided yet
I haven't added it it might come but I
have other things that I want to do
first so we'll see what happens now
introspection and reflection I guess if
you do everything at run time and
everything is cells cells and everything
is object then introspection and
reflection you get kind of for free
right yeah everything is mutable
everything is runtime if you have an
object that you're really unsure of if
say for example one of the things that
most of the reflective facilities are
actually and methods on the object
itself so you can ask y'all know before
what cells it has and stuff like that
but as it turns out those things if if
you create a really weird object that
doesn't really have an parents say for
example in in Ruby you have this
constant about blank slates a blank
slate is an object that doesn't really
define anything and undefined so all the
methods so you can do it to to use uses
for the Builder pattern for example if
you have one of those blank slates in
ioki they're they're really even more
blank than they are in Ruby and they're
released it's great because the only
thing you need to do is create a new
object and just remove all this mimics
and then you suddenly have a blank slate
yeah
and that's basically basically get the
collection of mimics and set them to now
yeah that's not exactly what you do it's
the collection of mimics are more like a
list are you just clear
okay but anyway if you do that that
object is not gonna respond to all of
the regular questions about what it
mimics or what Celsius has and stuff
like that because it doesn't have those
methods yeah so I have this specific
specific orbital reflector and the
reflector can be used to introspect
another on other objects so you can
basically say okay reflector other cells
and send it and obviously you get back
those cells even though if even if that
albeit this is a blank slate it can be
kind of simulate those objects having
methods yes almost but not all methods
just Annette this needed for reflection
in a moment so in the core code where I
really need to be able to handle
everything I use the reflector to make
sure that if I have weird objects like
that I can I can handle them too another
nice thing that I saw when I read the
well I wouldn't call it wellmaybe
specification tutorial kind of thing its
aspects mmm yeah so the aspect facility
is it's not really that weird it's
actually oaky itself and it's pretty
basic yeah it's actually just based
around the fact that I can wrap code
around other code and do that pretty
much automatically without me it's more
like lisps before and after methods yes
exactly it's it's very limited compared
to some of the cooler aspect systems
although I would argue that I mean I'm
not a very big fan of a Oh on code level
I think it's a good good concept for
designing systems you know thinking in
terms of viewpoints and aspects and
stuff but I think it's it's probably
enough if you have it on method level
and you don't probably want to you know
I don't know advise the third if
statement in the method body again yeah
exactly I mean that's the whole idea
behind how I did it because I think that
IO Keys is powerful enough as it is
without it I don't think that as
full-blown uh aspects would actually add
any interest in power bi okay yeah so
actually when I was first looking at I
okay I was actually somewhat
surprised that it's not a functional
language that there is assignment that's
kind of not that's not in line with the
current hype yeah I know I'm I'm a
revolutionary no I I to be honest I
don't really the whole the whole
functional hype right now it I mean I I
do kind of agree with it but it does
annoy me too from a language perspective
it's like okay
sure we have had functional languages
for 50 years now suddenly everyone is
doing them and it's really really cool
and everyone is thinking about the
concurrency problem yeah I don't find
the concurrency problem very interesting
so I wanted to explore something very
different so I didn't really feel the
need to make ioki functional I do think
it's there's definitely value or empower
in in being able to do mutable stuff and
and the kind of rampant mutability that
i oq have it's actually quite nice to be
able to do so yeah I mean nayaki doesn't
solve the concurrency problem at all so
you don't you don't have a specific
concurrency story for it at all there's
not at all right actually I mean I have
a few ideas the one thing that I'm gonna
add sooner or later is gonna be
transparent futures okay I'm also
thinking about doing something like
adding some of closures concurrency
primitives without either having the
requirement of stuff being immutable
yeah I think that it's possible in
language if you just trust your
developers to do the right thing and
ioki is definitely powerful enough that
you need to be able to trust that case I
mean immutability doesn't necessarily
buy you that much you can actually have
an STM and if people are just
responsible adults when they're
programming they can use that STM for
for kind of talking to each other over
threads but they still get the benefits
of mutability all over the place and I'm
not sure how that's gonna work out yeah
I'm gonna add it at some point but it's
definitely an idea okay that goes along
with the rest of I okey STM stands for
software transactional memory and a long
time ago we've had this episode and SEO
radio with I think Dan Grossman where we
discussed our
and the garbage collection so should we
define transparent future too
yeah why not so basically a future is an
object that you say okay sometime in the
future I want the result of evaluating
this function that result can be that
evaluation can start being done in
another thread but you don't do an
explicit thread creation or anything
like that and this is saying that it's
transparent means that when the object
is done being created or the value is
done being created it just replaces the
place where the future was stored okay
so it's not that you explicitly call you
know is value available blah blah but
you kind of magically pop it in exactly
so in scheme you have for example I
think it's called delay enforce so you
can say delay and then some code and
then when you say force you will
actually get the real value but you
always have to say force when you have
one of those things and I okay I will be
able to just let the let the real value
actually replace the the future object
another thing that I saw about
assignment is the statement that ioki
also supports assignment of places yes
place is kind of like Common Lisp set F
much for most of our listeners sorry
well the whole idea is that assignment
to name can be interesting sure but if
you allow assignment to a place that
means that you can modal assignment the
same way no matter what so for example
if you look at the say for example
sometimes you really want to assign a
cell that you can't really express this
a message name so the whole thing of
doing x equals 1 doesn't really work if
X is a message that say for example you
want to assign the empty message yeah
you can't really say mm-hmm equals 1
that doesn't really work so you need a
way to be able to assign these kind of
things and the way I oaky allows you to
to work with cells that you have to name
the way you do reflection is by calling
cell and giving it a name what want you
but you can also say it's cell X and
then after the parentheses equal 1 to
assign to that place so in other words
could I could I try to explain it in a
way that says that the L value of an
expression can itself be something
that's computed yes exactly it can have
arguments okay so that's how that's how
it's a general feature that makes it
possible to do for example list
assignment using square parentheses but
it's a general thing you can define your
own places like that
okay now I get it okay I guess the last
feature that I want to get at before we
kind of look at the state and where it's
going and where people can get
information about Aoki is comprehensions
I know it's not unique to ioki but we
haven't talked about this concept in
general and su radio before very much so
what's the comprehension it's also a
list list comprehension right yeah so
comprehension they're pretty funny
because they're not really interesting
in ioki they they I made him I just
implemented them just for fun they they
were the first real thing I used my
syntax macros to do right because as it
turns out the comprehension is actually
just a piece of syntax that can be
transformed into applications of of map
and flatmap and filter so the the idea
of comprehension see if you have a math
background you you kind of really like
this concept because you can declare to
say that okay
take X from this collection of values
and Y from this collection of values
multiply them and then filter them out
if they were larger than this and then
return this result so it's a way of
declaratively kind of creating
collections of values of lists of values
in some sense it's a glorified for
statement right yes where you can
iterate over several things at the same
time and then and then use or do
something with the values from all these
iterations yeah but the difference is
that you're actually working with syntax
here so the syntax is on top of it's on
top of these operations so you don't see
all the calls if you actually look at
the expansion or two
: I okey the it's pretty hard to follow
the the combinations of map and flatmap
and stuff like that most interesting
comprehensions are actually combinations
of iteration nested iterations between
more two or more Corrections which turns
out to be coming quite annoying after a
while
follow okay so I guess that that
concludes our discussion about the
various features let's let's kind of
zoom out and take a look at the somewhat
bigger picture again so have you done
any actual kind of you know project work
or any actual real work as opposed to
experiments with with ioki any
experience or are other people doing
that or what's the state there no so far
it's it's mostly been experimenting I
mean I'm working with examples of
different kinds and quite a lot of a
yogi' stack or library is actually
implemented naoki itself so that some of
the evolution of the language I have at
least one colleague who's looking at
using it to as a code generating DSL
because you can do internal dia cells
really easily and IO keys so he was
thinking about doing and doing a bit
doing something that actually generates
code as it turns out I okie is really
slow so you don't really want to run it
at runtime okay it's based on the JVM
right well actually I mean it was first
created on top of the JVM but I also
have a see law report right now and the
way it works is not by generating byte
code but you basically just implemented
an interpreter in Java kind of yes it's
a because you can change the ASD at
runtime it turns out to be pretty tricky
to create a compiler for it yes exactly
and I dunno how to do it it's just a
small matter of engineering mm-hmm okay
that's what the nuclear fusion guys also
say absolutely or no I mean what I need
to do is basically have a good way of
compiling small pieces of bytecode and
then have an enol adacia scheme of
something so I can just throw the
bytecode away if it becomes invalidated
so it's gonna be I'm gonna have a
just-in-time compiler so
can but it's gonna it's also not that
interesting because be having it be fast
it's not really from an expressive edgy
standpoint yeah so where do you go from
here I mean there are I read something
about I IOPS and I okie and then some
other letter yeah so the first version
of a yogi was a okie zero the first
second one was IOPS the current one is
called ioki II the second one is gonna
be P and I'm probably thinking about
releasing P pretty soon it depends on I
I have a few things that I really want
to add to it too before I do that the
first one is something I called three
rewriting where right now the way you
work with with the messages das T's is
pretty much imparative but I want to
make a more declarative approach about
how to rewrite message changes and and
an AST s so I'm working on that one and
then I I'm not sure if that's gonna be
in P or not but I want to have an
intermediate language basically I want
to have a DSL in IO key for the
implementation of i/o key because I'm
getting fed up with having to work with
both the Java and the C sharp card yeah
okay so these these 0 E and P things are
basically fancy version numbers and the
different not different kinds of ioki
well it's both actually because the as
it turns out the my implementations
called Ikey C ikc is the sealer version
ikj is the Java version they have real
version numbers okay but the but the
letters kind of thing it's more of a it
is more of a versioning of the language
I try to be consistent when I actually
changed a real language okay I I make a
new so there's Anna milestones in the
evolution of language I can make new
releases of the of the runtimes without
actually changing that letter I
understand yeah okay so where can people
find more information about it if
they're interested
so I okey org have all the information
necessary you can you can get links to
the mailing list there
there is also an IRC channel it's pretty
quiet right now
but it goes through periods when people
talking quite a lot there though those
are really the main in the mailing list
obviously if you want to find out the
information about aoki ioki dot org is
the first place to start but if you have
questions the IRC channel the mailing
list definitely the best place okay any
conferences where you're going to talk
about it in the middle future yes that's
a good point I'm actually going to be
talking at it in malmö at 11:00 in the
beginning of November and I'm not sure
whether we're going to publish this
episode before that but let's hope
probably not actually
yeah after that I don't know if I have
anything lined up I've done several
talks about ioki this fall and and there
should be actually a tour coming up from
the jvm language summit about ioki okay
there's also if you search for Java soon
and ioki I did a hour-long talk there
what I showed some code and stuff like
that okay good I guess that that
finishes the the I okay discussion I
would if you have two more minutes I'd
like to take the chance and ask your
opinion about the general state of
languages maybe especially on the JVM we
have all this stuff coming out you know
Scala closure or language not JVM but
it's also it has been well I'm not sure
if it's still hype or whether it has
been a hype and you have all these
things like boo and f-sharp and all that
stuff on the on the CLR Aksum yeah I I
think that the language is definitely
encouraging I am happy to see that
there's finally I mean we've been
spending almost 15 years in a very you
know very boring language climate yeah I
was never happy with the idea that Java
is the is the real big language and you
can use Java for everything Java
definitely has it has its place but it's
the whole idea that one language is good
enough for for everything is just I
don't think that's true so I'm very
happy to see that people are finally
starting to focus on languages my
opinion the language is actually your
most important tool shooting the right
tool for the job
it's definitely what being program is
but I think it's great to see all these
different approaches being tried all
these different languages that are
focused on different things coming out
yeah any opinion on which one of those
will you know will last will have
lasting you know
oh I hope most of them will last
actually I mean several of them heart I
have reached the size now where they
will be I mean they might not be a big
big but they will definitely last I'm
personally very happy about those you're
I'm not surprised
I like closure Scala definitely has some
interesting ideas too but of all the jvm
languages closure is definitely my
favorite of the ones that I'm not biased
towards something I find very
interesting is that the distinction of
language and runtime platform like JVM
is CLR is becoming more important so you
can have many languages on the same VM
therefore giving you some kind of basic
interoperability yeah and I think this
is the good thing about JVM right now
son has definitely realized that they
can get more leverage shelf of JVM as a
platform roles taken a long time but I
think they're finally there exactly yeah
I mean I'm part of the jsr 292 expert
group that aims to add some features to
the DM that definitely will not help the
Java language but it's actually suited
to help the other languages yeah its
tail recursion going to be in there at
some point
we're looking at it it's not going to be
in Java 7 ok but we're definitely
looking at it and there are there is a
proof of concept and an implementation
for the for the DaVinci machine ok so
there is definitely a possibility that
we get every person even jobs in Java 8
ok good so anything else from your side
you want to add any words of wisdom any
closing remarks I don't have any words
of wisdom ok thank you for for being on
the show
bye all right
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team @ SC - radio net or if you're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot site Music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas on top
[Music]
you